 ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿The Anatomy of a Large-Scale Hypertextual﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Web Search Engine﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Sergey Brin and Lawrence Page﻿
﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Computer Science Department,﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94305, USA﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿sergey@cs.stanford.edu and page@cs.stanford.edu﻿
﻿
﻿Abstract﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿In this paper, we present Google, a prototype of a large-scale search engine which makes heavy﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿use of the structure present in hypertext. Google is designed to crawl and index the Web efficiently﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿and produce much more satisfying search results than existing systems. The prototype with a full﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿text and hyperlink database of at least 24 million pages is available at http://google.stanford.edu/﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿To engineer a search engine is a challenging task. Search engines index tens to hundreds of﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿millions of web pages involving a comparable number of distinct terms. They answer tens of﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿millions of queries every day. Despite the importance of large-scale search engines on the web,﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿very little academic research has been done on them. Furthermore, due to rapid advance in﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿technology and web proliferation, creating a web search engine today is very different from three﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿years ago. This paper provides an in-depth description of our large-scale web search engine -- the﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿first such detailed public description we know of to date. Apart from the problems of scaling﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿traditional search techniques to data of this magnitude, there are new technical challenges involved﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿with using the additional information present in hypertext to produce better search results. This﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿paper addresses this question of how to build a practical large-scale system which can exploit the﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿additional information present in hypertext. Also we look at the problem of how to effectively deal﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿with uncontrolled hypertext collections where anyone can publish anything they want.﻿
﻿
﻿Keywords﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿World Wide Web, Search Engines, Information Retrieval, PageRank, Google﻿
﻿
﻿1. Introduction﻿
﻿(Note: There are two versions of this paper -- a longer full version and a shorter printed version. The﻿
﻿ ﻿full version is available on the web and the conference CD-ROM.)﻿
﻿The web creates new challenges for information retrieval. The amount of information on the web is﻿
﻿growing rapidly, as well as the number of new users inexperienced in the art of web research. People are﻿
﻿likely to surf the web using its link graph, often starting with high quality human maintained indices﻿
﻿such as Yahoo! or with search engines. Human maintained lists cover popular topics effectively but are﻿
﻿subjective, expensive to build and maintain, slow to improve, and cannot cover all esoteric topics.﻿
﻿Automated search engines that rely on keyword matching usually return too many low quality matches.﻿
﻿To make matters worse, some advertisers attempt to gain people’s attention by taking measures meant to  ﻿
﻿mislead automated search engines. We have built a large-scale search engine which addresses many of﻿
﻿the problems of existing systems. It makes especially heavy use of the additional structure present in﻿
﻿hypertext to provide much higher quality search results. We chose our system name, Google, because it﻿
﻿is a common spelling of googol, or 10100 and fits well with our goal of building very large-scale search﻿
﻿engines.﻿
﻿
﻿1.1 Web Search Engines -- Scaling Up: 1994 - 2000﻿
﻿Search engine technology has had to scale dramatically to keep up with the growth of the web. In 1994,﻿
﻿one of the first web search engines, the World Wide Web Worm (WWWW) [McBryan 94] had an index﻿
﻿of 110,000 web pages and web accessible documents. As of November, 1997, the top search engines﻿
﻿claim to index from 2 million (WebCrawler) to 100 million web documents (from Search Engine﻿
﻿Watch). It is foreseeable that by the year 2000, a comprehensive index of the Web will contain over a﻿
﻿billion documents. At the same time, the number of queries search engines handle has grown incredibly﻿
﻿too. In March and April 1994, the World Wide Web Worm received an average of about 1500 queries﻿
﻿per day. In November 1997, Altavista claimed it handled roughly 20 million queries per day. With the﻿
﻿increasing number of users on the web, and automated systems which query search engines, it is likely﻿
﻿that top search engines will handle hundreds of millions of queries per day by the year 2000. The goal of﻿
﻿our system is to address many of the problems, both in quality and scalability, introduced by scaling﻿
﻿search engine technology to such extraordinary numbers.﻿
﻿
﻿1.2. Google: Scaling with the Web﻿
﻿Creating a search engine which scales even to today’s web presents many challenges. Fast crawling  ﻿
﻿technology is needed to gather the web documents and keep them up to date. Storage space must be used﻿
﻿efficiently to store indices and, optionally, the documents themselves. The indexing system must process﻿
﻿hundreds of gigabytes of data efficiently. Queries must be handled quickly, at a rate of hundreds to﻿
﻿thousands per second.﻿
﻿
﻿These tasks are becoming increasingly difficult as the Web grows. However, hardware performance and﻿
﻿cost have improved dramatically to partially offset the difficulty. There are, however, several notable﻿
﻿exceptions to this progress such as disk seek time and operating system robustness. In designing Google,﻿
﻿we have considered both the rate of growth of the Web and technological changes. Google is designed to﻿
﻿scale well to extremely large data sets. It makes efficient use of storage space to store the index. Its data﻿
﻿structures are optimized for fast and efficient access (see section 4.2). Further, we expect that the cost to﻿
﻿index and store text or HTML will eventually decline relative to the amount that will be available (see﻿
﻿Appendix B). This will result in favorable scaling properties for centralized systems like Google.﻿
﻿
﻿1.3 Design Goals﻿
﻿1.3.1 Improved Search Quality﻿
﻿
﻿Our main goal is to improve the quality of web search engines. In 1994, some people believed that a﻿
﻿complete search index would make it possible to find anything easily. According to Best of the Web﻿
﻿1994 -- Navigators, "The best navigation service should make it easy to find almost anything on the﻿
﻿Web (once all the data is entered)." However, the Web of 1997 is quite different. Anyone who has used﻿
﻿a search engine recently, can readily testify that the completeness of the index is not the only factor in﻿
﻿the quality of search results. "Junk results" often wash out any results that a user is interested in. In fact,﻿
﻿as of November 1997, only one of the top four commercial search engines finds itself (returns its own﻿
﻿search page in response to its name in the top ten results). One of the main causes of this problem is that﻿
﻿the number of documents in the indices has been increasing by many orders of magnitude, but the user’s  ﻿
﻿ability to look at documents has not. People are still only willing to look at the first few tens of results.﻿
﻿Because of this, as the collection size grows, we need tools that have very high precision (number of﻿
﻿relevant documents returned, say in the top tens of results). Indeed, we want our notion of "relevant" to﻿
﻿only include the very best documents since there may be tens of thousands of slightly relevant﻿
﻿documents. This very high precision is important even at the expense of recall (the total number of﻿
﻿relevant documents the system is able to return). There is quite a bit of recent optimism that the use of﻿
﻿more hypertextual information can help improve search and other applications [Marchiori 97] [Spertus﻿
﻿97] [Weiss 96] [Kleinberg 98]. In particular, link structure [Page 98] and link text provide a lot of﻿
﻿information for making relevance judgments and quality filtering. Google makes use of both link﻿
﻿structure and anchor text (see Sections 2.1 and 2.2).﻿
﻿
﻿1.3.2 Academic Search Engine Research﻿
﻿
﻿Aside from tremendous growth, the Web has also become increasingly commercial over time. In 1993,﻿
﻿1.5% of web servers were on .com domains. This number grew to over 60% in 1997. At the same time,﻿
﻿search engines have migrated from the academic domain to the commercial. Up until now most search﻿
﻿engine development has gone on at companies with little publication of technical details. This causes﻿
﻿search engine technology to remain largely a black art and to be advertising oriented (see Appendix A).﻿
﻿With Google, we have a strong goal to push more development and understanding into the academic﻿
﻿realm.﻿
﻿
﻿Another important design goal was to build systems that reasonable numbers of people can actually use.﻿
﻿Usage was important to us because we think some of the most interesting research will involve﻿
﻿leveraging the vast amount of usage data that is available from modern web systems. For example, there﻿
﻿are many tens of millions of searches performed every day. However, it is very difficult to get this data,﻿
﻿mainly because it is considered commercially valuable.﻿
﻿
﻿Our final design goal was to build an architecture that can support novel research activities on﻿
﻿large-scale web data. To support novel research uses, Google stores all of the actual documents it crawls﻿
﻿in compressed form. One of our main goals in designing Google was to set up an environment where﻿
﻿other researchers can come in quickly, process large chunks of the web, and produce interesting results﻿
﻿that would have been very difficult to produce otherwise. In the short time the system has been up, there﻿
﻿have already been several papers using databases generated by Google, and many others are underway.﻿
﻿Another goal we have is to set up a Spacelab-like environment where researchers or even students can﻿
﻿propose and do interesting experiments on our large-scale web data.﻿
﻿
﻿2. System Features﻿
﻿The Google search engine has two important features that help it produce high precision results. First, it﻿
﻿makes use of the link structure of the Web to calculate a quality ranking for each web page. This ranking﻿
﻿is called PageRank and is described in detail in [Page 98]. Second, Google utilizes link to improve﻿
﻿search results.﻿
﻿
﻿2.1 PageRank: Bringing Order to the Web﻿
﻿The citation (link) graph of the web is an important resource that has largely gone unused in existing﻿
﻿web search engines. We have created maps containing as many as 518 million of these hyperlinks, a﻿
﻿significant sample of the total. These maps allow rapid calculation of a web page’s "PageRank", an  ﻿
﻿objective measure of its citation importance that corresponds well with people’s subjective idea of  ﻿
﻿importance. Because of this correspondence, PageRank is an excellent way to prioritize the results of﻿
﻿web keyword searches. For most popular subjects, a simple text matching search that is restricted to web﻿
﻿page titles performs admirably when PageRank prioritizes the results (demo available at﻿
﻿google.stanford.edu). For the type of full text searches in the main Google system, PageRank also helps﻿
﻿a great deal.﻿
﻿
﻿2.1.1 Description of PageRank Calculation﻿
﻿
﻿Academic citation literature has been applied to the web, largely by counting citations or backlinks to a﻿
﻿given page. This gives some approximation of a page’s importance or quality. PageRank extends this  ﻿
﻿idea by not counting links from all pages equally, and by normalizing by the number of links on a page.﻿
﻿PageRank is defined as follows:﻿
﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿We assume page A has pages T1...Tn which point to it (i.e., are citations). The parameter d﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿is a damping factor which can be set between 0 and 1. We usually set d to 0.85. There are﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿more details about d in the next section. Also C(A) is defined as the number of links going﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿out of page A. The PageRank of a page A is given as follows:﻿
﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿PR(A) = (1-d) + d (PR(T1)/C(T1) + ... + PR(Tn)/C(Tn))﻿
﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Note that the PageRanks form a probability distribution over web pages, so the sum of all﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿web pages’ PageRanks will be one.  ﻿
﻿
﻿PageRank or PR(A) can be calculated using a simple iterative algorithm, and corresponds to the﻿
﻿principal eigenvector of the normalized link matrix of the web. Also, a PageRank for 26 million web﻿
﻿pages can be computed in a few hours on a medium size workstation. There are many other details﻿
﻿which are beyond the scope of this paper.﻿
﻿
﻿2.1.2 Intuitive Justification﻿
﻿
﻿PageRank can be thought of as a model of user behavior. We assume there is a "random surfer" who is﻿
﻿given a web page at random and keeps clicking on links, never hitting "back" but eventually gets bored﻿
﻿and starts on another random page. The probability that the random surfer visits a page is its PageRank.﻿
﻿And, the d damping factor is the probability at each page the "random surfer" will get bored and request﻿
﻿another random page. One important variation is to only add the damping factor d to a single page, or a﻿
﻿group of pages. This allows for personalization and can make it nearly impossible to deliberately﻿
﻿mislead the system in order to get a higher ranking. We have several other extensions to PageRank,﻿
﻿again see [Page 98].﻿
﻿
﻿Another intuitive justification is that a page can have a high PageRank if there are many pages that point﻿
﻿to it, or if there are some pages that point to it and have a high PageRank. Intuitively, pages that are well﻿
﻿cited from many places around the web are worth looking at. Also, pages that have perhaps only one﻿
﻿citation from something like the Yahoo! homepage are also generally worth looking at. If a page was not﻿
﻿high quality, or was a broken link, it is quite likely that Yahoo’s homepage would not link to it.  ﻿
﻿PageRank handles both these cases and everything in between by recursively propagating weights﻿
﻿through the link structure of the web.﻿
﻿2.2 Anchor Text﻿
﻿The text of links is treated in a special way in our search engine. Most search engines associate the text﻿
﻿of a link with the page that the link is on. In addition, we associate it with the page the link points to.﻿
﻿This has several advantages. First, anchors often provide more accurate descriptions of web pages than﻿
﻿the pages themselves. Second, anchors may exist for documents which cannot be indexed by a﻿
﻿text-based search engine, such as images, programs, and databases. This makes it possible to return web﻿
﻿pages which have not actually been crawled. Note that pages that have not been crawled can cause﻿
﻿problems, since they are never checked for validity before being returned to the user. In this case, the﻿
﻿search engine can even return a page that never actually existed, but had hyperlinks pointing to it.﻿
﻿However, it is possible to sort the results, so that this particular problem rarely happens.﻿
﻿
﻿This idea of propagating anchor text to the page it refers to was implemented in the World Wide Web﻿
﻿Worm [McBryan 94] especially because it helps search non-text information, and expands the search﻿
﻿coverage with fewer downloaded documents. We use anchor propagation mostly because anchor text﻿
﻿can help provide better quality results. Using anchor text efficiently is technically difficult because of﻿
﻿the large amounts of data which must be processed. In our current crawl of 24 million pages, we had﻿
﻿over 259 million anchors which we indexed.﻿
﻿
﻿2.3 Other Features﻿
﻿Aside from PageRank and the use of anchor text, Google has several other features. First, it has location﻿
﻿information for all hits and so it makes extensive use of proximity in search. Second, Google keeps track﻿
﻿of some visual presentation details such as font size of words. Words in a larger or bolder font are﻿
﻿weighted higher than other words. Third, full raw HTML of pages is available in a repository.﻿
﻿
﻿3 Related Work﻿
﻿Search research on the web has a short and concise history. The World Wide Web Worm (WWWW)﻿
﻿[McBryan 94] was one of the first web search engines. It was subsequently followed by several other﻿
﻿academic search engines, many of which are now public companies. Compared to the growth of the﻿
﻿Web and the importance of search engines there are precious few documents about recent search engines﻿
﻿[Pinkerton 94]. According to Michael Mauldin (chief scientist, Lycos Inc) [Mauldin], "the various﻿
﻿services (including Lycos) closely guard the details of these databases". However, there has been a fair﻿
﻿amount of work on specific features of search engines. Especially well represented is work which can﻿
﻿get results by post-processing the results of existing commercial search engines, or produce small scale﻿
﻿"individualized" search engines. Finally, there has been a lot of research on information retrieval﻿
﻿systems, especially on well controlled collections. In the next two sections, we discuss some areas where﻿
﻿this research needs to be extended to work better on the web.﻿
﻿
﻿3.1 Information Retrieval﻿
﻿Work in information retrieval systems goes back many years and is well developed [Witten 94].﻿
﻿However, most of the research on information retrieval systems is on small well controlled﻿
﻿homogeneous collections such as collections of scientific papers or news stories on a related topic.﻿
﻿Indeed, the primary benchmark for information retrieval, the Text Retrieval Conference [TREC 96],﻿
﻿uses a fairly small, well controlled collection for their benchmarks. The "Very Large Corpus"﻿
﻿benchmark is only 20GB compared to the 147GB from our crawl of 24 million web pages. Things that﻿
﻿work well on TREC often do not produce good results on the web. For example, the standard vector﻿
﻿space model tries to return the document that most closely approximates the query, given that both query﻿
﻿and document are vectors defined by their word occurrence. On the web, this strategy often returns very﻿
﻿short documents that are the query plus a few words. For example, we have seen a major search engine﻿
﻿return a page containing only "Bill Clinton Sucks" and picture from a "Bill Clinton" query. Some argue﻿
﻿that on the web, users should specify more accurately what they want and add more words to their﻿
﻿query. We disagree vehemently with this position. If a user issues a query like "Bill Clinton" they should﻿
﻿get reasonable results since there is a enormous amount of high quality information available on this﻿
﻿topic. Given examples like these, we believe that the standard information retrieval work needs to be﻿
﻿extended to deal effectively with the web.﻿
﻿
﻿3.2 Differences Between the Web and Well Controlled Collections﻿
﻿The web is a vast collection of completely uncontrolled heterogeneous documents. Documents on the﻿
﻿web have extreme variation internal to the documents, and also in the external meta information that﻿
﻿might be available. For example, documents differ internally in their language (both human and﻿
﻿programming), vocabulary (email addresses, links, zip codes, phone numbers, product numbers), type or﻿
﻿format (text, HTML, PDF, images, sounds), and may even be machine generated (log files or output﻿
﻿from a database). On the other hand, we define external meta information as information that can be﻿
﻿inferred about a document, but is not contained within it. Examples of external meta information include﻿
﻿things like reputation of the source, update frequency, quality, popularity or usage, and citations. Not﻿
﻿only are the possible sources of external meta information varied, but the things that are being measured﻿
﻿vary many orders of magnitude as well. For example, compare the usage information from a major﻿
﻿homepage, like Yahoo’s which currently receives millions of page views every day with an obscure  ﻿
﻿historical article which might receive one view every ten years. Clearly, these two items must be treated﻿
﻿very differently by a search engine.﻿
﻿
﻿Another big difference between the web and traditional well controlled collections is that there is﻿
﻿virtually no control over what people can put on the web. Couple this flexibility to publish anything with﻿
﻿the enormous influence of search engines to route traffic and companies which deliberately﻿
﻿manipulating search engines for profit become a serious problem. This problem that has not been﻿
﻿addressed in traditional closed information retrieval systems. Also, it is interesting to note that metadata﻿
﻿efforts have largely failed with web search engines, because any text on the page which is not directly﻿
﻿represented to the user is abused to manipulate search engines. There are even numerous companies﻿
﻿which specialize in manipulating search engines for profit.﻿
﻿
﻿4 System Anatomy﻿
﻿First, we will provide a high level discussion of the architecture. Then, there is some in-depth﻿
﻿descriptions of important data structures. Finally, the major applications: crawling, indexing, and﻿
﻿searching will be examined in depth.﻿
﻿4.1 Google Architecture Overview﻿
﻿In this section, we will give a high level overview of how﻿
﻿the whole system works as pictured in Figure 1. Further﻿
﻿sections will discuss the applications and data structures﻿
﻿not mentioned in this section. Most of Google is﻿
﻿implemented in C or C++ for efficiency and can run in﻿
﻿either Solaris or Linux.﻿
﻿
﻿In Google, the web crawling (downloading of web pages)﻿
﻿is done by several distributed crawlers. There is a﻿
﻿URLserver that sends lists of URLs to be fetched to the﻿
﻿crawlers. The web pages that are fetched are then sent to﻿
﻿the storeserver. The storeserver then compresses and stores﻿
﻿the web pages into a repository. Every web page has an﻿
﻿associated ID number called a docID which is assigned﻿
﻿whenever a new URL is parsed out of a web page. The﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Figure 1. High Level Google Architecture﻿
﻿indexing function is performed by the indexer and the﻿
﻿sorter. The indexer performs a number of functions. It reads﻿
﻿the repository, uncompresses the documents, and parses them. Each document is converted into a set of﻿
﻿word occurrences called hits. The hits record the word, position in document, an approximation of font﻿
﻿size, and capitalization. The indexer distributes these hits into a set of "barrels", creating a partially﻿
﻿sorted forward index. The indexer performs another important function. It parses out all the links in﻿
﻿every web page and stores important information about them in an anchors file. This file contains﻿
﻿enough information to determine where each link points from and to, and the text of the link.﻿
﻿
﻿The URLresolver reads the anchors file and converts relative URLs into absolute URLs and in turn into﻿
﻿docIDs. It puts the anchor text into the forward index, associated with the docID that the anchor points﻿
﻿to. It also generates a database of links which are pairs of docIDs. The links database is used to compute﻿
﻿PageRanks for all the documents.﻿
﻿
﻿The sorter takes the barrels, which are sorted by docID (this is a simplification, see Section 4.2.5), and﻿
﻿resorts them by wordID to generate the inverted index. This is done in place so that little temporary﻿
﻿space is needed for this operation. The sorter also produces a list of wordIDs and offsets into the﻿
﻿inverted index. A program called DumpLexicon takes this list together with the lexicon produced by the﻿
﻿indexer and generates a new lexicon to be used by the searcher. The searcher is run by a web server and﻿
﻿uses the lexicon built by DumpLexicon together with the inverted index and the PageRanks to answer﻿
﻿queries.﻿
﻿
﻿4.2 Major Data Structures﻿
﻿Google’s data structures are optimized so that a large document collection can be crawled, indexed, and  ﻿
﻿searched with little cost. Although, CPUs and bulk input output rates have improved dramatically over﻿
﻿the years, a disk seek still requires about 10 ms to complete. Google is designed to avoid disk seeks﻿
﻿whenever possible, and this has had a considerable influence on the design of the data structures.﻿
﻿4.2.1 BigFiles﻿
﻿
﻿BigFiles are virtual files spanning multiple file systems and are addressable by 64 bit integers. The﻿
﻿allocation among multiple file systems is handled automatically. The BigFiles package also handles﻿
﻿allocation and deallocation of file descriptors, since the operating systems do not provide enough for our﻿
﻿needs. BigFiles also support rudimentary compression options.﻿
﻿
﻿4.2.2 Repository﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿The repository contains the full HTML of every web page.﻿
﻿Each page is compressed using zlib (see RFC1950). The﻿
﻿choice of compression technique is a tradeoff between speed﻿
﻿and compression ratio. We chose zlib’s speed over a  ﻿
﻿significant improvement in compression offered by bzip. The﻿
﻿compression rate of bzip was approximately 4 to 1 on the﻿
﻿repository as compared to zlib’s 3 to 1 compression. In the  ﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Figure 2. Repository Data Structure﻿
﻿repository, the documents are stored one after the other and﻿
﻿are prefixed by docID, length, and URL as can be seen in﻿
﻿Figure 2. The repository requires no other data structures to be used in order to access it. This helps with﻿
﻿data consistency and makes development much easier; we can rebuild all the other data structures from﻿
﻿only the repository and a file which lists crawler errors.﻿
﻿
﻿4.2.3 Document Index﻿
﻿
﻿The document index keeps information about each document. It is a fixed width ISAM (Index sequential﻿
﻿access mode) index, ordered by docID. The information stored in each entry includes the current﻿
﻿document status, a pointer into the repository, a document checksum, and various statistics. If the﻿
﻿document has been crawled, it also contains a pointer into a variable width file called docinfo which﻿
﻿contains its URL and title. Otherwise the pointer points into the URLlist which contains just the URL.﻿
﻿This design decision was driven by the desire to have a reasonably compact data structure, and the﻿
﻿ability to fetch a record in one disk seek during a search﻿
﻿
﻿Additionally, there is a file which is used to convert URLs into docIDs. It is a list of URL checksums﻿
﻿with their corresponding docIDs and is sorted by checksum. In order to find the docID of a particular﻿
﻿URL, the URL’s checksum is computed and a binary search is performed on the checksums file to find  ﻿
﻿its docID. URLs may be converted into docIDs in batch by doing a merge with this file. This is the﻿
﻿technique the URLresolver uses to turn URLs into docIDs. This batch mode of update is crucial because﻿
﻿otherwise we must perform one seek for every link which assuming one disk would take more than a﻿
﻿month for our 322 million link dataset.﻿
﻿
﻿4.2.4 Lexicon﻿
﻿
﻿The lexicon has several different forms. One important change from earlier systems is that the lexicon﻿
﻿can fit in memory for a reasonable price. In the current implementation we can keep the lexicon in﻿
﻿memory on a machine with 256 MB of main memory. The current lexicon contains 14 million words﻿
﻿(though some rare words were not added to the lexicon). It is implemented in two parts -- a list of the﻿
﻿words (concatenated together but separated by nulls) and a hash table of pointers. For various functions,﻿
﻿the list of words has some auxiliary information which is beyond the scope of this paper to explain fully.﻿
﻿
﻿4.2.5 Hit Lists﻿
﻿
﻿A hit list corresponds to a list of occurrences of a particular word in a particular document including﻿
﻿position, font, and capitalization information. Hit lists account for most of the space used in both the﻿
﻿forward and the inverted indices. Because of this, it is important to represent them as efficiently as﻿
﻿possible. We considered several alternatives for encoding position, font, and capitalization -- simple﻿
﻿encoding (a triple of integers), a compact encoding (a hand optimized allocation of bits), and Huffman﻿
﻿coding. In the end we chose a hand optimized compact encoding since it required far less space than the﻿
﻿simple encoding and far less bit manipulation than Huffman coding. The details of the hits are shown in﻿
﻿Figure 3.﻿
﻿
﻿Our compact encoding uses two bytes for every hit. There are two types of hits: fancy hits and plain hits.﻿
﻿Fancy hits include hits occurring in a URL, title, anchor text, or meta tag. Plain hits include everything﻿
﻿else. A plain hit consists of a capitalization bit, font size, and 12 bits of word position in a document (all﻿
﻿positions higher than 4095 are labeled 4096). Font size is represented relative to the rest of the document﻿
﻿using three bits (only 7 values are actually used because 111 is the flag that signals a fancy hit). A fancy﻿
﻿hit consists of a capitalization bit, the font size set to 7 to indicate it is a fancy hit, 4 bits to encode the﻿
﻿type of fancy hit, and 8 bits of position. For anchor hits, the 8 bits of position are split into 4 bits for﻿
﻿position in anchor and 4 bits for a hash of the docID the anchor occurs in. This gives us some limited﻿
﻿phrase searching as long as there are not that many anchors for a particular word. We expect to update﻿
﻿the way that anchor hits are stored to allow for greater resolution in the position and docIDhash fields.﻿
﻿We use font size relative to the rest of the document because when searching, you do not want to rank﻿
﻿otherwise identical documents differently just because one of the documents is in a larger font.﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿The length of a hit list is stored before the hits themselves.﻿
﻿To save space, the length of the hit list is combined with the﻿
﻿wordID in the forward index and the docID in the inverted﻿
﻿index. This limits it to 8 and 5 bits respectively (there are﻿
﻿some tricks which allow 8 bits to be borrowed from the﻿
﻿wordID). If the length is longer than would fit in that many﻿
﻿bits, an escape code is used in those bits, and the next two﻿
﻿bytes contain the actual length.﻿
﻿
﻿4.2.6 Forward Index﻿
﻿
﻿The forward index is actually already partially sorted. It is﻿
﻿stored in a number of barrels (we used 64). Each barrel﻿
﻿holds a range of wordID’s. If a document contains words  ﻿
﻿that fall into a particular barrel, the docID is recorded into﻿
﻿the barrel, followed by a list of wordID’s with hitlists which Figure 3. Forward and Reverse Indexes  ﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿and the Lexicon﻿
﻿correspond to those words. This scheme requires slightly﻿
﻿more storage because of duplicated docIDs but the﻿
﻿difference is very small for a reasonable number of buckets and saves considerable time and coding﻿
﻿complexity in the final indexing phase done by the sorter. Furthermore, instead of storing actual﻿
﻿wordID’s, we store each wordID as a relative difference from the minimum wordID that falls into the  ﻿
﻿barrel the wordID is in. This way, we can use just 24 bits for the wordID’s in the unsorted barrels,  ﻿
﻿leaving 8 bits for the hit list length.﻿
﻿
﻿4.2.7 Inverted Index﻿
﻿
﻿The inverted index consists of the same barrels as the forward index, except that they have been﻿
﻿processed by the sorter. For every valid wordID, the lexicon contains a pointer into the barrel that﻿
﻿wordID falls into. It points to a doclist of docID’s together with their corresponding hit lists. This doclist  ﻿
﻿represents all the occurrences of that word in all documents.﻿
﻿
﻿An important issue is in what order the docID’s should appear in the doclist. One simple solution is to  ﻿
﻿store them sorted by docID. This allows for quick merging of different doclists for multiple word﻿
﻿queries. Another option is to store them sorted by a ranking of the occurrence of the word in each﻿
﻿document. This makes answering one word queries trivial and makes it likely that the answers to﻿
﻿multiple word queries are near the start. However, merging is much more difficult. Also, this makes﻿
﻿development much more difficult in that a change to the ranking function requires a rebuild of the index.﻿
﻿We chose a compromise between these options, keeping two sets of inverted barrels -- one set for hit﻿
﻿lists which include title or anchor hits and another set for all hit lists. This way, we check the first set of﻿
﻿barrels first and if there are not enough matches within those barrels we check the larger ones.﻿
﻿
﻿4.3 Crawling the Web﻿
﻿Running a web crawler is a challenging task. There are tricky performance and reliability issues and﻿
﻿even more importantly, there are social issues. Crawling is the most fragile application since it involves﻿
﻿interacting with hundreds of thousands of web servers and various name servers which are all beyond﻿
﻿the control of the system.﻿
﻿
﻿In order to scale to hundreds of millions of web pages, Google has a fast distributed crawling system. A﻿
﻿single URLserver serves lists of URLs to a number of crawlers (we typically ran about 3). Both the﻿
﻿URLserver and the crawlers are implemented in Python. Each crawler keeps roughly 300 connections﻿
﻿open at once. This is necessary to retrieve web pages at a fast enough pace. At peak speeds, the system﻿
﻿can crawl over 100 web pages per second using four crawlers. This amounts to roughly 600K per second﻿
﻿of data. A major performance stress is DNS lookup. Each crawler maintains a its own DNS cache so it﻿
﻿does not need to do a DNS lookup before crawling each document. Each of the hundreds of connections﻿
﻿can be in a number of different states: looking up DNS, connecting to host, sending request, and﻿
﻿receiving response. These factors make the crawler a complex component of the system. It uses﻿
﻿asynchronous IO to manage events, and a number of queues to move page fetches from state to state.﻿
﻿
﻿It turns out that running a crawler which connects to more than half a million servers, and generates tens﻿
﻿of millions of log entries generates a fair amount of email and phone calls. Because of the vast number﻿
﻿of people coming on line, there are always those who do not know what a crawler is, because this is the﻿
﻿first one they have seen. Almost daily, we receive an email something like, "Wow, you looked at a lot of﻿
﻿pages from my web site. How did you like it?" There are also some people who do not know about the﻿
﻿robots exclusion protocol, and think their page should be protected from indexing by a statement like,﻿
﻿"This page is copyrighted and should not be indexed", which needless to say is difficult for web crawlers﻿
﻿to understand. Also, because of the huge amount of data involved, unexpected things will happen. For﻿
﻿example, our system tried to crawl an online game. This resulted in lots of garbage messages in the﻿
﻿middle of their game! It turns out this was an easy problem to fix. But this problem had not come up﻿
﻿until we had downloaded tens of millions of pages. Because of the immense variation in web pages and﻿
﻿servers, it is virtually impossible to test a crawler without running it on large part of the Internet.﻿
﻿Invariably, there are hundreds of obscure problems which may only occur on one page out of the whole﻿
﻿web and cause the crawler to crash, or worse, cause unpredictable or incorrect behavior. Systems which﻿
﻿access large parts of the Internet need to be designed to be very robust and carefully tested. Since large﻿
﻿complex systems such as crawlers will invariably cause problems, there needs to be significant resources﻿
﻿devoted to reading the email and solving these problems as they come up.﻿
﻿
﻿4.4 Indexing the Web﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Parsing -- Any parser which is designed to run on the entire Web must handle a huge array of﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿possible errors. These range from typos in HTML tags to kilobytes of zeros in the middle of a tag,﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿non-ASCII characters, HTML tags nested hundreds deep, and a great variety of other errors that﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿challenge anyone’s imagination to come up with equally creative ones. For maximum speed,  ﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿instead of using YACC to generate a CFG parser, we use flex to generate a lexical analyzer which﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿we outfit with its own stack. Developing this parser which runs at a reasonable speed and is very﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿robust involved a fair amount of work.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Indexing Documents into Barrels -- After each document is parsed, it is encoded into a number﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿of barrels. Every word is converted into a wordID by using an in-memory hash table -- the lexicon.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿New additions to the lexicon hash table are logged to a file. Once the words are converted into﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿wordID’s, their occurrences in the current document are translated into hit lists and are written into  ﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿the forward barrels. The main difficulty with parallelization of the indexing phase is that the﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿lexicon needs to be shared. Instead of sharing the lexicon, we took the approach of writing a log of﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿all the extra words that were not in a base lexicon, which we fixed at 14 million words. That way﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿multiple indexers can run in parallel and then the small log file of extra words can be processed by﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿one final indexer.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Sorting -- In order to generate the inverted index, the sorter takes each of the forward barrels and﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿sorts it by wordID to produce an inverted barrel for title and anchor hits and a full text inverted﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿barrel. This process happens one barrel at a time, thus requiring little temporary storage. Also, we﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿parallelize the sorting phase to use as many machines as we have simply by running multiple﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿sorters, which can process different buckets at the same time. Since the barrels don’t fit into main  ﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿memory, the sorter further subdivides them into baskets which do fit into memory based on﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿wordID and docID. Then the sorter, loads each basket into memory, sorts it and writes its contents﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿into the short inverted barrel and the full inverted barrel.﻿
﻿
﻿4.5 Searching﻿
﻿The goal of searching is to provide quality search results efficiently. Many of the large commercial﻿
﻿search engines seemed to have made great progress in terms of efficiency. Therefore, we have focused﻿
﻿more on quality of search in our research, although we believe our solutions are scalable to commercial﻿
﻿volumes with a bit more effort. The google query evaluation process is show in Figure 4.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1. Parse the query.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿2. Convert words into wordIDs.﻿
﻿To put a limit on response time, once a certain number﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿3. Seek to the start of the doclist in﻿
﻿(currently 40,000) of matching documents are found, the﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿the short barrel for every word.﻿
﻿searcher automatically goes to step 8 in Figure 4. This﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿4. Scan through the doclists until﻿
﻿means that it is possible that sub-optimal results would be﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿there is a document that matches﻿
﻿returned. We are currently investigating other ways to solve﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿all the search terms.﻿
﻿this problem. In the past, we sorted the hits according to﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿5. Compute the rank of that﻿
﻿PageRank, which seemed to improve the situation.﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿document for the query.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿6. If we are in the short barrels and at﻿
﻿4.5.1 The Ranking System﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿the end of any doclist, seek to the﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿start of the doclist in the full barrel﻿
﻿Google maintains much more information about web﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿for every word and go to step 4.﻿
﻿documents than typical search engines. Every hitlist﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿7. If we are not at the end of any﻿
﻿includes position, font, and capitalization information.﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿doclist go to step 4.﻿
﻿Additionally, we factor in hits from anchor text and the﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Sort the documents that have﻿
﻿PageRank of the document. Combining all of this﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿matched by rank and return the top﻿
﻿information into a rank is difficult. We designed our ranking﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿k.﻿
﻿function so that no particular factor can have too much﻿
﻿influence. First, consider the simplest case -- a single word﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Figure 4. Google Query Evaluation﻿
﻿query. In order to rank a document with a single word﻿
﻿query, Google looks at that document’s hit list for that word.  ﻿
﻿Google considers each hit to be one of several different types (title, anchor, URL, plain text large font,﻿
﻿plain text small font, ...), each of which has its own type-weight. The type-weights make up a vector﻿
﻿indexed by type. Google counts the number of hits of each type in the hit list. Then every count is﻿
﻿converted into a count-weight. Count-weights increase linearly with counts at first but quickly taper off﻿
﻿so that more than a certain count will not help. We take the dot product of the vector of count-weights﻿
﻿with the vector of type-weights to compute an IR score for the document. Finally, the IR score is﻿
﻿combined with PageRank to give a final rank to the document.﻿
﻿
﻿For a multi-word search, the situation is more complicated. Now multiple hit lists must be scanned﻿
﻿through at once so that hits occurring close together in a document are weighted higher than hits﻿
﻿occurring far apart. The hits from the multiple hit lists are matched up so that nearby hits are matched﻿
﻿together. For every matched set of hits, a proximity is computed. The proximity is based on how far﻿
﻿apart the hits are in the document (or anchor) but is classified into 10 different value "bins" ranging from﻿
﻿a phrase match to "not even close". Counts are computed not only for every type of hit but for every type﻿
﻿and proximity. Every type and proximity pair has a type-prox-weight. The counts are converted into﻿
﻿count-weights and we take the dot product of the count-weights and the type-prox-weights to compute﻿
﻿an IR score. All of these numbers and matrices can all be displayed with the search results using a﻿
﻿special debug mode. These displays have been very helpful in developing the ranking system.﻿
﻿
﻿4.5.2 Feedback﻿
﻿
﻿The ranking function has many parameters like the type-weights and the type-prox-weights. Figuring out﻿
﻿the right values for these parameters is something of a black art. In order to do this, we have a user﻿
﻿feedback mechanism in the search engine. A trusted user may optionally evaluate all of the results that﻿
﻿are returned. This feedback is saved. Then when we modify the ranking function, we can see the impact﻿
﻿of this change on all previous searches which were ranked. Although far from perfect, this gives us some﻿
﻿idea of how a change in the ranking function affects the search results.﻿
﻿
﻿5 Results and Performance﻿
﻿
﻿The most important measure of a search﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Query: bill clinton﻿
﻿engine is the quality of its search results.﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.whitehouse.gov/﻿
﻿While a complete user evaluation is﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿100.00%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(no date) (0K)﻿
﻿beyond the scope of this paper, our own﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.whitehouse.gov/﻿
﻿experience with Google has shown it to﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Office of the President﻿
﻿produce better results than the major﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿99.67%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(Dec 23 1996) (2K)﻿
﻿commercial search engines for most﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.whitehouse.gov/WH/EOP/OP/html/OP_Home.html﻿
﻿searches. As an example which illustrates﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Welcome To The White House﻿
﻿the use of PageRank, anchor text, and﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿99.98%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(Nov 09 1997) (5K)﻿
﻿proximity, Figure 4 shows Google’s  ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.whitehouse.gov/WH/Welcome.html﻿
﻿results for a search on "bill clinton".﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Send Electronic Mail to the President﻿
﻿These results demonstrates some of﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿99.86%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(Jul 14 1997) (5K)﻿
﻿Google’s features. The results are  ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.whitehouse.gov/WH/Mail/html/Mail_President.html﻿
﻿clustered by server. This helps﻿
﻿considerably when sifting through result﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿mailto:president@whitehouse.gov﻿
﻿sets. A number of results are from the﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿99.98%﻿
﻿whitehouse.gov domain which is what﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿mailto:President@whitehouse.gov﻿
﻿one may reasonably expect from such a﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿99.27%﻿
﻿search. Currently, most major commercial﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿The "Unofficial" Bill Clinton﻿
﻿search engines do not return any results﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿94.06%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(Nov 11 1997) (14K)﻿
﻿from whitehouse.gov, much less the right﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://zpub.com/un/un-bc.html﻿
﻿ones. Notice that there is no title for the﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Bill Clinton Meets The Shrinks﻿
﻿first result. This is because it was not﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿86.27%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(Jun 29 1997) (63K)﻿
﻿crawled. Instead, Google relied on anchor﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://zpub.com/un/un-bc9.html﻿
﻿text to determine this was a good answer﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿President Bill Clinton - The Dark Side﻿
﻿to the query. Similarly, the fifth result is﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿97.27%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(Nov 10 1997) (15K)﻿
﻿an email address which, of course, is not﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.realchange.org/clinton.htm﻿
﻿crawlable. It is also a result of anchor text.﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿$3 Bill Clinton﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿94.73%﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(no date) (4K)﻿
﻿All of the results are reasonably high﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.gatewy.net/~tjohnson/clinton1.html﻿
﻿quality pages and, at last check, none﻿
﻿were broken links. This is largely because﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Figure 4. Sample Results from Google﻿
﻿they all have high PageRank. The﻿
﻿PageRanks are the percentages in red﻿
﻿along with bar graphs. Finally, there are no results about a Bill other than Clinton or about a Clinton﻿
﻿other than Bill. This is because we place heavy importance on the proximity of word occurrences. Of﻿
﻿course a true test of the quality of a search engine would involve an extensive user study or results﻿
﻿analysis which we do not have room for here. Instead, we invite the reader to try Google for themselves﻿
﻿at http://google.stanford.edu.﻿
﻿
﻿5.1 Storage Requirements﻿
﻿Aside from search quality, Google is designed to scale cost effectively to the size of the Web as it﻿
﻿grows. One aspect of this is to use storage efficiently. Table 1 has a breakdown of some statistics and﻿
﻿storage requirements of Google. Due to compression the total size of the repository is about 53 GB, just﻿
﻿over one third of the total data it stores. At current disk prices this makes the repository a relatively﻿
﻿cheap source of useful data. More importantly, the total of all the data used by the search engine requires﻿
﻿a comparable amount of storage, about 55 GB. Furthermore, most queries can be answered using just the﻿
﻿short inverted index. With better encoding and compression of the Document Index, a high quality web﻿
﻿search engine may fit onto a 7GB drive of a new PC.﻿
﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Storage Statistics﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Total Size of Fetched Pages 147.8 GB﻿
﻿5.2 System Performance﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Compressed Repository﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿53.5 GB﻿
﻿It is important for a search engine to crawl and index﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Short Inverted Index﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿4.1 GB﻿
﻿efficiently. This way information can be kept up to date and﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Full Inverted Index﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿37.2 GB﻿
﻿major changes to the system can be tested relatively quickly.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Lexicon﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿293 MB﻿
﻿For Google, the major operations are Crawling, Indexing,﻿
﻿and Sorting. It is difficult to measure how long crawling﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Temporary Anchor Data﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿6.6 GB﻿
﻿took overall because disks filled up, name servers crashed,﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿(not in total)﻿
﻿or any number of other problems which stopped the system.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Document Index Incl.﻿
﻿In total it took roughly 9 days to download the 26 million﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿9.7 GB﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Variable Width Data﻿
﻿pages (including errors). However, once the system was﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Links Database﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿3.9 GB﻿
﻿running smoothly, it ran much faster, downloading the last﻿
﻿11 million pages in just 63 hours, averaging just over 4﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Total Without Repository 55.2 GB﻿
﻿million pages per day or 48.5 pages per second. We ran the﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Total With Repository 108.7 GB﻿
﻿indexer and the crawler simultaneously. The indexer ran just﻿
﻿faster than the crawlers. This is largely because we spent just﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Web Page Statistics﻿
﻿enough time optimizing the indexer so that it would not be a﻿
﻿bottleneck. These optimizations included bulk updates to the﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Number of Web Pages﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿24 million﻿
﻿document index and placement of critical data structures on﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Fetched﻿
﻿the local disk. The indexer runs at roughly 54 pages per﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Number of Urls Seen﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿76.5 million﻿
﻿second. The sorters can be run completely in parallel; using﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Number of Email﻿
﻿four machines, the whole process of sorting takes about 24﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.7 million﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Addresses﻿
﻿hours.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Number of 404’s  ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.6 million﻿
﻿5.3 Search Performance﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Table 1. Statistics﻿
﻿Improving the performance of search was not the major focus of our research up to this point. The﻿
﻿current version of Google answers most queries in between 1 and 10 seconds. This time is mostly﻿
﻿dominated by disk IO over NFS (since disks are spread over a number of machines). Furthermore,﻿
﻿Google does not have any optimizations such as query caching, subindices on common terms, and other﻿
﻿common optimizations. We intend to speed up Google considerably through distribution and hardware,﻿
﻿software, and algorithmic improvements. Our target is to be able to handle several hundred queries per﻿
﻿second. Table 2 has some sample query times from the current version of Google. They are repeated to﻿
﻿show the speedups resulting from cached IO.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Same Query﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Initial Query﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Repeated (IO﻿
﻿6 Conclusions﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿mostly cached)﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿CPU﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Total CPU﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Total﻿
﻿Google is designed to be a scalable search engine.﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Query﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Time(s) Time(s) Time(s) Time(s)﻿
﻿The primary goal is to provide high quality search﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿al gore﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿0.09﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿2.13﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿0.06﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿0.06﻿
﻿results over a rapidly growing World Wide Web.﻿
﻿Google employs a number of techniques to improve﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿vice﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.77﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿3.84﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.66﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.80﻿
﻿search quality including page rank, anchor text, and﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿president﻿
﻿proximity information. Furthermore, Google is a﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿hard﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿0.25﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿4.86﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿0.20﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿0.24﻿
﻿complete architecture for gathering web pages,﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿disks﻿
﻿indexing them, and performing search queries over﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿search﻿
﻿them.﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.31﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿9.63﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.16﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1.16﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿engines﻿
﻿6.1 Future Work﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Table 2. Search Times﻿
﻿A large-scale web search engine is a complex system and much remains to be done. Our immediate﻿
﻿goals are to improve search efficiency and to scale to approximately 100 million web pages. Some﻿
﻿simple improvements to efficiency include query caching, smart disk allocation, and subindices.﻿
﻿Another area which requires much research is updates. We must have smart algorithms to decide what﻿
﻿old web pages should be recrawled and what new ones should be crawled. Work toward this goal has﻿
﻿been done in [Cho 98]. One promising area of research is using proxy caches to build search databases,﻿
﻿since they are demand driven. We are planning to add simple features supported by commercial search﻿
﻿engines like boolean operators, negation, and stemming. However, other features are just starting to be﻿
﻿explored such as relevance feedback and clustering (Google currently supports a simple hostname based﻿
﻿clustering). We also plan to support user context (like the user’s location), and result summarization. We  ﻿
﻿are also working to extend the use of link structure and link text. Simple experiments indicate PageRank﻿
﻿can be personalized by increasing the weight of a user’s home page or bookmarks. As for link text, we  ﻿
﻿are experimenting with using text surrounding links in addition to the link text itself. A Web search﻿
﻿engine is a very rich environment for research ideas. We have far too many to list here so we do not﻿
﻿expect this Future Work section to become much shorter in the near future.﻿
﻿
﻿6.2 High Quality Search﻿
﻿The biggest problem facing users of web search engines today is the quality of the results they get back.﻿
﻿While the results are often amusing and expand users’ horizons, they are often frustrating and consume  ﻿
﻿precious time. For example, the top result for a search for "Bill Clinton" on one of the most popular﻿
﻿commercial search engines was the Bill Clinton Joke of the Day: April 14, 1997. Google is designed to﻿
﻿provide higher quality search so as the Web continues to grow rapidly, information can be found easily.﻿
﻿In order to accomplish this Google makes heavy use of hypertextual information consisting of link﻿
﻿structure and link (anchor) text. Google also uses proximity and font information. While evaluation of a﻿
﻿search engine is difficult, we have subjectively found that Google returns higher quality search results﻿
﻿than current commercial search engines. The analysis of link structure via PageRank allows Google to﻿
﻿evaluate the quality of web pages. The use of link text as a description of what the link points to helps﻿
﻿the search engine return relevant (and to some degree high quality) results. Finally, the use of proximity﻿
﻿information helps increase relevance a great deal for many queries.﻿
﻿6.3 Scalable Architecture﻿
﻿Aside from the quality of search, Google is designed to scale. It must be efficient in both space and time,﻿
﻿and constant factors are very important when dealing with the entire Web. In implementing Google, we﻿
﻿have seen bottlenecks in CPU, memory access, memory capacity, disk seeks, disk throughput, disk﻿
﻿capacity, and network IO. Google has evolved to overcome a number of these bottlenecks during﻿
﻿various operations. Google’s major data structures make efficient use of available storage space.  ﻿
﻿Furthermore, the crawling, indexing, and sorting operations are efficient enough to be able to build an﻿
﻿index of a substantial portion of the web -- 24 million pages, in less than one week. We expect to be able﻿
﻿to build an index of 100 million pages in less than a month.﻿
﻿
﻿6.4 A Research Tool﻿
﻿In addition to being a high quality search engine, Google is a research tool. The data Google has﻿
﻿collected has already resulted in many other papers submitted to conferences and many more on the﻿
﻿way. Recent research such as [Abiteboul 97] has shown a number of limitations to queries about the﻿
﻿Web that may be answered without having the Web available locally. This means that Google (or a﻿
﻿similar system) is not only a valuable research tool but a necessary one for a wide range of applications.﻿
﻿We hope Google will be a resource for searchers and researchers all around the world and will spark the﻿
﻿next generation of search engine technology.﻿
﻿
﻿7 Acknowledgments﻿
﻿Scott Hassan and Alan Steremberg have been critical to the development of Google. Their talented﻿
﻿contributions are irreplaceable, and the authors owe them much gratitude. We would also like to thank﻿
﻿Hector Garcia-Molina, Rajeev Motwani, Jeff Ullman, and Terry Winograd and the whole WebBase﻿
﻿group for their support and insightful discussions. Finally we would like to recognize the generous﻿
﻿support of our equipment donors IBM, Intel, and Sun and our funders. The research described here was﻿
﻿conducted as part of the Stanford Integrated Digital Library Project, supported by the National Science﻿
﻿Foundation under Cooperative Agreement IRI-9411306. Funding for this cooperative agreement is also﻿
﻿provided by DARPA and NASA, and by Interval Research, and the industrial partners of the Stanford﻿
﻿Digital Libraries Project.﻿
﻿
﻿References﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Best of the Web 1994 -- Navigators http://botw.org/1994/awards/navigators.html﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Bill Clinton Joke of the Day: April 14, 1997. http://www.io.com/~cjburke/clinton/970414.html.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Bzip2 Homepage http://www.muraroa.demon.co.uk/﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Google Search Engine http://google.stanford.edu/﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Harvest http://harvest.transarc.com/﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Mauldin, Michael L. Lycos Design Choices in an Internet Search Service, IEEE Expert Interview﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.computer.org/pubs/expert/1997/trends/x1008/mauldin.htm﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿The Effect of Cellular Phone Use Upon Driver Attention﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://www.webfirst.com/aaa/text/cell/cell0toc.htm﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Search Engine Watch http://www.searchenginewatch.com/﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿RFC 1950 (zlib) ftp://ftp.uu.net/graphics/png/documents/zlib/zdoc-index.html﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Robots Exclusion Protocol: http://info.webcrawler.com/mak/projects/robots/exclusion.htm﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Web Growth Summary: http://www.mit.edu/people/mkgray/net/web-growth-summary.html﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Yahoo! http://www.yahoo.com/﻿
﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Abiteboul 97] Serge Abiteboul and Victor Vianu, Queries and Computation on the Web.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Proceedings of the International Conference on Database Theory. Delphi, Greece 1997.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Bagdikian 97] Ben H. Bagdikian. The Media Monopoly. 5th Edition. Publisher: Beacon, ISBN:﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿0807061557﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Cho 98] Junghoo Cho, Hector Garcia-Molina, Lawrence Page. Efficient Crawling Through URL﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Ordering. Seventh International Web Conference (WWW 98). Brisbane, Australia, April 14-18,﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1998.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Gravano 94] Luis Gravano, Hector Garcia-Molina, and A. Tomasic. The Effectiveness of GlOSS﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿for the Text-Database Discovery Problem. Proc. of the 1994 ACM SIGMOD International﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Conference On Management Of Data, 1994.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Kleinberg 98] Jon Kleinberg, Authoritative Sources in a Hyperlinked Environment, Proc.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms, 1998.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Marchiori 97] Massimo Marchiori. The Quest for Correct Information on the Web: Hyper Search﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Engines. The Sixth International WWW Conference (WWW 97). Santa Clara, USA, April 7-11,﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1997.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[McBryan 94] Oliver A. McBryan. GENVL and WWWW: Tools for Taming the Web. First﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿International Conference on the World Wide Web. CERN, Geneva (Switzerland), May 25-26-27﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿1994. http://www.cs.colorado.edu/home/mcbryan/mypapers/www94.ps﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Page 98] Lawrence Page, Sergey Brin, Rajeev Motwani, Terry Winograd. The PageRank Citation﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Ranking: Bringing Order to the Web. Manuscript in progress.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://google.stanford.edu/~backrub/pageranksub.ps﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Pinkerton 94] Brian Pinkerton, Finding What People Want: Experiences with the WebCrawler.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿The Second International WWW Conference Chicago, USA, October 17-20, 1994.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿http://info.webcrawler.com/bp/WWW94.html﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Spertus 97] Ellen Spertus. ParaSite: Mining Structural Information on the Web. The Sixth﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿International WWW Conference (WWW 97). Santa Clara, USA, April 7-11, 1997.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[TREC 96] Proceedings of the fifth Text REtrieval Conference (TREC-5). Gaithersburg, Maryland,﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿November 20-22, 1996. Publisher: Department of Commerce, National Institute of Standards and﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Technology. Editors: D. K. Harman and E. M. Voorhees. Full text at: http://trec.nist.gov/﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Witten 94] Ian H Witten, Alistair Moffat, and Timothy C. Bell. Managing Gigabytes:﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Compressing and Indexing Documents and Images. New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold, 1994.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿[Weiss 96] Ron Weiss, Bienvenido Velez, Mark A. Sheldon, Chanathip Manprempre, Peter﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Szilagyi, Andrzej Duda, and David K. Gifford. HyPursuit: A Hierarchical Network Search Engine﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿that Exploits Content-Link Hypertext Clustering. Proceedings of the 7th ACM Conference on﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Hypertext. New York, 1996.﻿
﻿
﻿Vitae﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Sergey Brin received his B.S. degree in mathematics and computer science﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿from the University of Maryland at College Park in 1993. Currently, he is a﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Ph.D. candidate in computer science at Stanford University where he received﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿his M.S. in 1995. He is a recipient of a National Science Foundation Graduate﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Fellowship. His research interests include search engines, information﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿extraction from unstructured sources, and data mining of large text collections﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿and scientific data.﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Lawrence Page was born in East Lansing, Michigan, and received a B.S.E.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿in Computer Engineering at the University of Michigan Ann Arbor in 1995.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿He is currently a Ph.D. candidate in Computer Science at Stanford University.﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿Some of his research interests include the link structure of the web, human﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿computer interaction, search engines, scalability of information access﻿
﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿ ﻿interfaces, and personal data mining.﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿
﻿8 Appendix A: Advertising and Mixed Motives﻿
﻿Currently, the predominant business model for commercial search engines is advertising. The goals of﻿
﻿the advertising business model do not always correspond to providing quality search to users. For﻿
﻿example, in our prototype search engine one of the top results for cellular phone is "The Effect of﻿
﻿Cellular Phone Use Upon Driver Attention", a study which explains in great detail the distractions and﻿
﻿risk associated with conversing on a cell phone while driving. This search result came up first because﻿
﻿of its high importance as judged by the PageRank algorithm, an approximation of citation importance on﻿
﻿the web [Page, 98]. It is clear that a search engine which was taking money for showing cellular phone﻿
﻿ads would have difficulty justifying the page that our system returned to its paying advertisers. For this﻿
﻿type of reason and historical experience with other media [Bagdikian 83], we expect that advertising﻿
﻿funded search engines will be inherently biased towards the advertisers and away from the needs of the﻿
﻿consumers.﻿
﻿
﻿Since it is very difficult even for experts to evaluate search engines, search engine bias is particularly﻿
﻿insidious. A good example was OpenText, which was reported to be selling companies the right to be﻿
﻿listed at the top of the search results for particular queries [Marchiori 97]. This type of bias is much﻿
﻿more insidious than advertising, because it is not clear who "deserves" to be there, and who is willing to﻿
﻿pay money to be listed. This business model resulted in an uproar, and OpenText has ceased to be a﻿
﻿viable search engine. But less blatant bias are likely to be tolerated by the market. For example, a search﻿
﻿engine could add a small factor to search results from "friendly" companies, and subtract a factor from﻿
﻿results from competitors. This type of bias is very difficult to detect but could still have a significant﻿
﻿effect on the market. Furthermore, advertising income often provides an incentive to provide poor﻿
﻿quality search results. For example, we noticed a major search engine would not return a large airline’s  ﻿
﻿homepage when the airline’s name was given as a query. It so happened that the airline had placed an  ﻿
﻿expensive ad, linked to the query that was its name. A better search engine would not have required this﻿
﻿ad, and possibly resulted in the loss of the revenue from the airline to the search engine. In general, it﻿
﻿could be argued from the consumer point of view that the better the search engine is, the fewer﻿
﻿advertisements will be needed for the consumer to find what they want. This of course erodes the﻿
﻿advertising supported business model of the existing search engines. However, there will always be﻿
﻿money from advertisers who want a customer to switch products, or have something that is genuinely﻿
﻿new. But we believe the issue of advertising causes enough mixed incentives that it is crucial to have a﻿
﻿competitive search engine that is transparent and in the academic realm.﻿
﻿
﻿9 Appendix B: Scalability﻿
﻿9. 1 Scalability of Google﻿
﻿We have designed Google to be scalable in the near term to a goal of 100 million web pages. We have﻿
﻿just received disk and machines to handle roughly that amount. All of the time consuming parts of the﻿
﻿system are parallelize and roughly linear time. These include things like the crawlers, indexers, and﻿
﻿sorters. We also think that most of the data structures will deal gracefully with the expansion. However,﻿
﻿at 100 million web pages we will be very close up against all sorts of operating system limits in the﻿
﻿common operating systems (currently we run on both Solaris and Linux). These include things like﻿
﻿addressable memory, number of open file descriptors, network sockets and bandwidth, and many others.﻿
﻿We believe expanding to a lot more than 100 million pages would greatly increase the complexity of our﻿
﻿system.﻿
﻿
﻿9.2 Scalability of Centralized Indexing Architectures﻿
﻿As the capabilities of computers increase, it becomes possible to index a very large amount of text for a﻿
﻿reasonable cost. Of course, other more bandwidth intensive media such as video is likely to become﻿
﻿more pervasive. But, because the cost of production of text is low compared to media like video, text is﻿
﻿likely to remain very pervasive. Also, it is likely that soon we will have speech recognition that does a﻿
﻿reasonable job converting speech into text, expanding the amount of text available. All of this provides﻿
﻿amazing possibilities for centralized indexing. Here is an illustrative example. We assume we want to﻿
﻿index everything everyone in the US has written for a year. We assume that there are 250 million people﻿
﻿in the US and they write an average of 10k per day. That works out to be about 850 terabytes. Also﻿
﻿assume that indexing a terabyte can be done now for a reasonable cost. We also assume that the﻿
﻿indexing methods used over the text are linear, or nearly linear in their complexity. Given all these﻿
﻿assumptions we can compute how long it would take before we could index our 850 terabytes for a﻿
﻿reasonable cost assuming certain growth factors. Moore’s Law was defined in 1965 as a doubling every  ﻿
﻿18 months in processor power. It has held remarkably true, not just for processors, but for other﻿
﻿important system parameters such as disk as well. If we assume that Moore’s law holds for the future,  ﻿
﻿we need only 10 more doublings, or 15 years to reach our goal of indexing everything everyone in the﻿
﻿US has written for a year for a price that a small company could afford. Of course, hardware experts are﻿
﻿somewhat concerned Moore’s Law may not continue to hold for the next 15 years, but there are  ﻿
﻿certainly a lot of interesting centralized applications even if we only get part of the way to our﻿
﻿hypothetical example.﻿
﻿Of course a distributed systems like Gloss [Gravano 94] or Harvest will often be the most efficient and﻿
﻿elegant technical solution for indexing, but it seems difficult to convince the world to use these systems﻿
﻿because of the high administration costs of setting up large numbers of installations. Of course, it is﻿
﻿quite likely that reducing the administration cost drastically is possible. If that happens, and everyone﻿
﻿starts running a distributed indexing system, searching would certainly improve drastically.﻿
﻿
﻿Because humans can only type or speak a finite amount, and as computers continue improving, text﻿
﻿indexing will scale even better than it does now. Of course there could be an infinite amount of machine﻿
﻿generated content, but just indexing huge amounts of human generated content seems tremendously﻿
﻿useful. So we are optimistic that our centralized web search engine architecture will improve in its﻿
﻿ability to cover the pertinent text information over time and that there is a bright future for search.﻿
